Leser, Paul; Papers ger058
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Paul Leser Papers
1850-1984
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Leser, Paul, 1899-
ger058
95 cubic ft.
The Paul Leser Papers document not only the life and career of anthropologist Paul Leser, but also contain materials pertaining to Leser's sister, Maria Lingemann and her husband Heinrich Lingemann, and earlier members of the Leser family. Although the collection contains correspondence between Paul and his brother, Albert (Leser) Lestoque, a separate collection, the Albert (Leser) Lestoque Papers, documents the life and career of Paul Leser's brother as well as providing additional Leser family documents and material.
Biographical Sketch
Paul Leser was born on February 23, 1899 in Frankfurt am Main, Germany, the youngest of Wilhelm and Helene (Rikoff) Leser's three children. He attended schools in Frankfurt and was graduated from the Goethe Gymnasium in 1917 with his Abitur. That year, Leser was inducted into the German Army and served in World War I; he later became ill and recuperated in the Army Hospital. During his hospitalization, he began taking classes at the University of Bonn. In 1919, he became a member of the Nerother-Bund, a part of the German youth movement which was founded by the brothers Karl and Robert Oelbermann. Also in that year, he returned to the University of Bonn to study under his mentor Fritz Graebner, one of the principal exponents of the cultural-historical approach to ethnology. He graduated from the University of Bonn with his Ph.D. in 1925.
Leser held positions at the Frankfurter Bund für Volksbildung and at the Ethnological Museum in Frankfurt before becoming a Privatdozent for Ethnology at the Darmstadt Institute of Technology. During this time period he became involved in the case against Dr. Julius Lips of the Raustenstrauch-Joest Museum, who was accused by Leser and others of plagiarizing from the works of Graebner, Schmidt, and Koppers. The case dragged on until 1933, when many of the participants were removed from their positions by the Nazis. Though the case took up much of his time in the early 1930's, his main interest was his own work on the history of the plow. In 1931, his most renowned work Entstehunq und Verbreitung des Pfluges was published (it was eventually reprinted in Denmark in 1971).
In 1936, because of the increasingly hostile political climate in Germany, Leser was forced to immigrate to Sweden. He took a position as translator for Folk-Liv in Stockholm. In 1941, he immigrated to the United States. Leser served in the United States Army in North Africa, Sicily, and Italy from 1942-1945. After the war, and a brief stint as a civilian employee at the U.S. War Department, Leser returned to the world of academia. Beginning in 1947, he held positions as Professor of Anthropology at Olivet College in Michigan, Black Mountain College in North Carolina, and The Hartford Seminary Foundation in Connecticut. In 1967, he retired from his teaching position at the Hartford Seminary and became an Emeritus member of the faculty. At the time of his death in December of 1984, Leser was a Research Professor of Anthropology at the University of Hartford. Leser died in Hartford at the age of 85 and was buried in the family plot in a cemetery in Frankfurt am Main.
Chronology of Events:
1899 February 23, born in Frankfurt am Main, Germany to Wilhelm and Helene (Rikoff) Leser.
1908-1917 Attended Goethe Gymnasium in Frankfurt
1917-1919 Served in the German Army
1917-1918 Attended the University of Bonn while in Army Hospital
1919-1924 Attended the University of Frankfurt and the University of Bonn
1919-1936 Member of the Nerother Wandervogel
1925 Graduated with Ph.D. from University of Bonn
1924-1933 Lecturer in Ethnology, Frankfurter Bund für Volksbildung
1928-1933 Junior Assistant Curator, Ethnological Museum, Frankfurt am Main
1929-1933 Privatdozent for Ethnology, Darmstadt Institute of Technology
1931 Publication of major work Entstehung und Verbreitung des Pfluges
1936 Immigrated to Sweden
1937-1941 Translator for Folk-Liv, Stockholm, Sweden
1941 Immigrated to the United States
1942-1945 Served in U.S. Army in N. Africa, Sicily, and Italy
1945-1947 Civilian employee, U.S. War Dept.
1947-1949 Professor of Anthropology, Olivet College, Olivet, Michigan
1949-1951 Professor of Anthropology, Black Mountain College, Black Mountain, North Carolina.
1951-1952 Assistant Professor of Anthropology, The Hartford Seminary Foundation, Hartford, CT
1952-1967 Professor of Anthropology, The Hartford Seminary Foundation
1957 Visiting Professor of Anthropology, New School for Social Research, New York, NY
1958 Summer, Visiting Professor of Ethnology, University of Cologne, Germany
1966-1967 Visiting Professor (Fulbright scholar) University of Vienna, Austria 1967 Emeritus, Hartford Seminary Foundation
1967 Emeritus, Hartford Seminary Foundation
1968-1984 President of the Permanent International Committee for Research on the History of Agricultural Implements
1976-1984 Research Professor of Anthropology, University of Hartford
1984 December 21, died in Hartford, CT.
Scope and Contents
The Paul Leser Papers consist of 95 cu. ft. of materials, 1850-1984. The collection, rich in family history, documents, and correspondence, documents not only the life and career of anthropologist Paul Leser, but also contains materials pertaining to Leser's sister, Maria Lingemann and her husband Heinrich Lingemann, and earlier members of the Leser family. Although the collection contains correspondence between Paul and his brother, Albert (Leser) Lestoque, a separate collection, the Albert (Leser) Lestoque Papers, documents the life and career of Paul Leser's brother as well as providing additional Leser family documents and material.
In addition to numerous family materials and related correspondence, the collection also contains: Leser's vast correspondence with fellow anthropologists and ethnologists, colleagues, students, and life-long friends; a sizable reprint collection; manuscripts, typescripts and published versions of Leser's own writings; course notes, materials and student files.
Two series in the collection of special interest to researchers are the materials pertaining to the ethnologist and mentor of Paul Leser, Fritz Graeber, and the collection of materials pertaining to Julius Lips (see descriptions below).
The collection is divided into twenty-one series: 1) Biographical materials, documents, 1882-1984; 2) Diaries, notebooks, account books, address books, 1914-1983; 3) Family and legal correspondence, 1850-1984; 4) Maria (Mira) and Heinrich (Heinz) Lingemann Collection, 1913-1964; 5) General Correspondence, 1913-1984; 6) Correspondence with institutions, associations, publishers, etc., 1920-1984; 7) Writings of Paul Leser, 1914-1979; 8) Fritz Graebner Collection, 1909-1980; 9) Julius Lips Collection, 1926-1940; 10) Jugendbewegung Collection, 1913-1984; 11) Course (teaching) materials, ca. 1926-1974; 12) Notes on various topics, notebooks, 1915-1974; 13) Photographs, negatives, slides, ca. 1900-1980; 14) Manuscripts, reprints and publications by other authors; 15) Pamphlets; 16) Hartford Seminary Foundation materials, 1950-1984; 17) Student records/papers, ca. 1948-1976; 18) Clippings on individuals; 19) Materials on various subjects; 20) Miscellaneous memorabilia; and 21) Periodicals.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Walter Leser, nephew of Paul Leser, in 1985.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Agriculture; Anthropology; Anthropologists--Germany; Anthropologists--United States; Anthropologists--Sweden; Ethnologists--Sweden; Ethnologists--Germany; Ethnologists--United States; Ethnology--Methodology; Germans--Sweden; Germans--Denmark; Germans--United States; Youth--Germany--Societies and clubs; Frankfurt am Main (Germany)--Societies and clubs; Correspondence; Diaries; Notebooks; Interviews; Photographs; Leser, Paul, 1899-; Herskovits, Melville J. (Melville Jean), 1895-1963; Lestoque, Albert; Leser, Albert; Johanson, Donald C.; Lips, Julius, 1895-1950; Staudinger, Hans, 1889-1980; Schaber, Will; Graebner, Fritz, 1877-1934; Goodman, Paul; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Nerother Wandervogel (Society: Germany); Hartford Theological Seminary; Black Mountain College (Black Mountain, N.C.); Frankfurter Bund für Volksbildung; Museum für Völkerkunde Frankfurt am Main
- Series 1 - Biographical materials, documents, 1882-1984; 1; 108 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into three sections: documents pertaining directly to Paul Leser, documents pertaining to other family members, and newspaper clippings primarily about Paul Leser. Included in this series are materials pertaining to the Leser family residence, located in the Plittersdorf section of Bonn, Germany, and include documentation of the estate, details of the original land purchase, wartime confiscation by the Nazis, later restitution claims, and final sale of the property in 1972.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Birth certificate, early documents, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 1)
  - Documents, 1945+ (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 2)
  - Confirmation notebook, 1914 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 3)
  - Rheinische Friedrich Wilhelms Universität, Bonn, 1924-1929 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 4)
  - Recommendation letters (Ernst Vatter, A. von LeCoq), 1927 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 5)
  - Technische Hochschule, Darmstadt, 1927-1932 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 6)
  - Frankfurter Bund für Volksbildung, 1929-1932 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 7)
  - Leser's attempt to emigrate to Peru, 1939-1940 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 8)
  - Immigration to U.S., 1942 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 9)
  - Naturalization papers, 1942 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 10)
  - U. S. Army service, 1942-1945 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 11)
  - Unemployment, 1945; 1947 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 12)
  - U.S. Military Intelligence questionnaire, 1945 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 13)
    Applications for employment.
  - U.S. Military Intelligence Service, 1945-1947 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 14)
  - U.S. Military Intelligence -- miscellaneous materials, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 15)
  - Civil Service applications, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 16)
  - Employment inquiries, 1949-1950 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 17)
  - Employment in other countries, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 18)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation, 1951-1966 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 19)
  - Trip to Africa, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 20)
  - Guest lecturer, Universität Köln, 1958 Summer (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 21)
  - Address lists, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 22)
  - Book lists, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 23)
  - Curriculum vitae, early (German and English), Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 24)
  - Curriculum vitae, Spanish, ca. 1939 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 25)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1945 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 26)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1948-1949 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 27)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 28)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1958; 1967 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 29)
  - Gifts to relatives, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 30)
  - Bibliography, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 31)
  - 80th birthday commemorative bibliography, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 32)
  - Courses taught, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 33)
  - Names of prominent students, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 34)
  - References, excerpts from reference letters, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 35)
  - References, War Department, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 36)
    Carl E. Brose, Arthur W. Curtis, Walter P. Hertz, Edmond M. Rowan, Howard B. Smith, Mercer C. Walter, C. Warndorf, J. H. Zimmermann.
  - Reference letters, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 37)
    Franz Boas, Sigurd Erixon, Robert Heine-Geldern, Lawrence Herman, Milton Horn, Gerhard Lindblom, Lucien Scherman, Franz Weidenreich, Karl A. Wittfogel.
  - Reviews of writings, extracts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 38)
  - Passport applications, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 39)
  - Passports, identification cards, etc., Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 40)
  - Driver's licenses, eye glass prescriptions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 41)
  - Entschädigungsprozess (Restitution case): Paul Leser vs. Land Hessen, 1958 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 42)
  - List of personal possessions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 43)
  - Travel insurance documents, Undated (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 44)
  - Trust agreement, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 45)
  - Last Will and Testament, early versions, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 1)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 2)
  - Stationery, calling cards, etc., Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 3)
  - Stock purchases, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 4)
  - Tax documents, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 5)
  - Tax records, 1971; 1972 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 6)
  - Tax documents, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 7)
  - Tax records, 1977 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 8)
  - Tax records, 1978 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 9)
  - Tax documents, 1982-1984 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 10)
  - Excerpts on the Leser family from Will Schaber's work, A Tale of Two Continents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 11)
  - Leser family geneology, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 12)
  - Leser family documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 13)
  - Rikoff family documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 14)
  - Family gravesites, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 15)
  - Ludwig Leser'sche Stiftung in Frankfurt am Main, 1907 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 16)
  - Leser'sche Familienstiftung taxes 1946-1952, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 17)
  - Leser'sche Familienstiftung correspondence (55 Büchelstrasse), Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 18)
  - Leser, Helene Rikoff. Documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 19)
  - Leser, Helene Rikoff. Albums, 1882; 1899 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 20)
  - Leser, Helene Rikoff. Death certificate, gravesite, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 21)
  - Cahn family documents (ancestors of Helene Rikoff Leser), Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 22)
  - Cahn/Rikoff account books, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 23)
  - Leser, Wilhelm. Documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 24)
  - [Leser, Wilhelm]. Notebooks, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 25)
  - Leser, Wilhelm and Helene Rikoff. Marriage documents, 1891 (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 26)
  - Leser, Wilhelm. Death certificate, gravesite, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 27)
  - Leser, Emil; Leser, Bertha. Documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 28)
  - Leser, Philipp; Leser, Charlotte. Documents, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 29)
  - [Leser, Philipp]. Notebook, Undated (Box 2 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 30)
  - Villa Cahn, Plittersdorf. History, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 1)
  - Purchase documents, Plittersdorf property, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 2)
  - Plittersdorf tax documents, 1937 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 3)
  - Plittersdorf art work; photos; catalog, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 4)
  - Documents dealing with Plittersdorf property, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 5)
  - Legal proceedings: Walter P. Leser vs. Rheinpark Grundstück- Gesellschaft, 1976 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 6)
  - Sale of Plittersdorf property, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 7)
  - Autobiographical statement by Paul Leser, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 8)
  - Transcripts of interviews of Paul Leser, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 9-10)
  - Paul Leser's birthday dictionary, Undated (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 11)
  - Leser family clippings, 1920-1923 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 12)
  - Clippings (Dean & Douglas Coon), 1969-1971 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 13)
  - Clippings about Paul Leser, 1.88
    - Clippings, 1924-1929; 1932 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 14)
    - Clippings, 1941 November (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 15)
    - Clippings, 1941 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 16)
    - Clippings, 1947-1948 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 1951 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 18)
    - Clippings, 1952 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 19)
    - Clippings, 1953 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 20)
    - Clippings, 1956 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 21)
    - Clippings, 1959 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 22)
    - Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 23)
    - Clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 24)
    - Clippings, 1966 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 25)
    - Clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 26)
    - Clippings, 1977 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 27)
    - Clippings, 1979 February 16 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 28)
    - Clippings, 1979 February 22 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 29)
    - Clippings, 1979 February 23 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 30)
    - Clippings, 1979 March-1979 April (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 31)
    - Clippings, 1981; 1983 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 32)
    - Clippings, obituaries, 1984 (Box 3 (1-Series 1 - Biographical materials, ), Folder 33)
- Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, address books, 1914-1983; 2; 60 file folders
  This series contains a number of Leser's early diaries (1914-1922) as well as a number from the last decade of his life (1973-1982). Calendars and appointment books date from 1923-1983. This series also contains a card address file, as well as personal address/telephone books.
  Arranged chronologically, plus one box containing index cards with addresses, and several address/telephone books.
  - Student notebooks, 1914; Undated (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 1)
  - Diary: I, 1. Januar 1915 bis 20. Februar 1915 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 2)
  - Diary: II, 20. Februar 1915 bis 8. Mai 1915 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 3)
  - Diary: III, 8. Mai 1915 bis 29. Juni 1915 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 4)
  - Diary: IV, 30. Juni 1915 bis 20. August 1915 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 5)
  - Diary: V, 20. August 1915 bis 3. November 1915 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 6)
  - Diary: VI, 3. November 1915 bis 26. März 1916 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 7)
    Missing.
  - Diary: VII, 26. März 1916 bis 8. Juli 1916 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 8)
  - Diary: VIII, 8. Juli 1916 bis 15. September 1916 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 9)
  - Diary: IX, 16. September 1916 bis 19. November 1916 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 10)
  - Diary: X, 19. November 1916 bis 17. Februar 1917 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 11)
  - Diary: XI, 17. Februar 1917 bis (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 12)
  - Diary: XII, 21. Mai 1917 bis (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 13)
  - Diary, 1919 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 14)
  - Tagebuch, Ende Juni 1921 bis 16. November 1921 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 15)
  - Diary, 27. II. 1922- (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 16)
  - Diary, 11. VI. 1922- (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 17)
  - Diary, 1942 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 18)
  - Diary, 28. Juli 1951-13. April 1953 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 19)
  - Diary, 15. November 1973-9. Mai 1974 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 20)
  - Diary, 1974 July 03-1975 September (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 21)
  - Diary, 24. August 1978 bis 16. Juni 1979 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 22)
  - Diary, 17. Juni 1979 bis 8. April 1980 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 23)
  - Hinweise, Vermerke, Entwürfe, ab 25. Dezember 1979 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 24)
  - Diary, 9. April 1980-14. November 1980 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 25)
  - Diary, 15. November 1980- (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 26)
  - Tagebuch, begonnen am [started on] 24. Oktober 1982 (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 27)
  - Diary, 14. November 1982- (Box 4 (2-Series 2 - Diaries, notebooks, account books, ), Folder 28)